当我们开始谈论机器人和传感器的需求时，很多人的问题
When we start talking about robots and the need for sensors, the question that many people
问：'为什么我们不使用GPS，当然这已经足够了？'。GPS无处不在-它是
ask is: ‘Why don’t we just use GPS, surely that’s enough?’. GPS is everywhere—it’s
在我们的手机中，它在我们的汽车中...它告诉我们我们在哪里。让我们谈一点
in our phones, it’s in our cars … it tells us where we are. So let’s talk a little
关于GPS。想象一下，我们在地面上有一个机器人
bit about GPS. Imagine we have a robot on the ground and
它的头部有一个GPS接收器。在天空中有许多低卫星
it’s got a GPS receiver in its head. In the sky are a number of satellites in low
地球轨道，他们都发送无线电波，机器人的GPS接收器
earth orbit, and they are all sending radio waves which the GPS receiver in the robot’s
头可以拿起来。利用无线电波所需的时间
head can pick up. Using the time that it takes the radio wave
从每颗卫星到机器人，我们可以计算出每颗卫星到机器人的距离。
to travel from each satellite to the robot we can work out the distance from each satellite to the robot.
如果我们知道足够的距离-我们知道卫星在太空中的位置-
If we know enough of these distances—we know where the satellites are in space—
那么我们就可以找出机器人的位置。
then we can work out where the robot is.
这是GPS的基本原理。现在这些无线电波的频率非常高;
That’s the fundamental principle of GPS. Now these radio waves are at a very high frequency;
它们大约在1.5千兆赫兹左右，这很重要，我们将讨论为什么会这样
they are around about 1.5 gigahertz, and that’s significant and we’ll talk about why that’s
重要的是。想象一下，现在我们正在向上看
significant shortly. Imagine now we’re looking upwards from the
机器人。我们仰望天空，我们可以拥有许多卫星
robot. We’re looking up to the sky, and there are a number of satellites that we can
看到。事实上，我们只需要四颗卫星来计算我们在这个星球上的位置。那是
see. We only need four satellites in fact, to work out where we are on the planet. That’s
获得所谓“修复”的最低要求。
the minimum requirement in order to get what’s called a ‘fix’.
现在想象一下我们的机器人在城市环境中。想象一下，我们正在一条街上
Now imagine that our robot is in an urban environment. Imagine we’re on a street in
曼哈顿或类似的东西。所以现在发生的是天空的某些部分
Manhattan or something like that. So what happens now is that some part of the sky is
模糊。我们看不到所有的卫星。现在我们只能看到两颗卫星
obscured. We can’t see all of the satellites. Now we can only see two satellites and that’s
不足以获得修复。这是一种非常普遍的现象，这就是我们遇到问题的原因
not enough to obtain a fix. This is a very common phenomenon, that’s why we have problems
在城市环境中使用GPS。但它也发生在其他环境中。它可以发生
with GPS in urban environments. But it occurs in other environments as well. It can occur
也许是在一个非常非常深的采矿坑里，坑的墙壁掩盖了一个重要的地方
perhaps in a very, very deep mining pit where the walls of the pit obscure a significant
天空的一部分。现在想象我们有我们的机器人而且它是
fraction of the sky. Now imagine that we have our robot and it’s
在一些大型工业园区。有大型的墙壁和烟囱和结构
at some big industrial complex. There are large walls and chimneys and structures made
没有金属。现在在这种情况下发生的是来自卫星的信号可能
out of metal. Now what happens in this case is that the signals from the satellite may
不能直接前往机器人。它们可能会从这些金属中弹出一些
not travel in a direct line to the robot. They may bounce off some of these metallic
结构在击中机器人之前。问题在于信号有
structures before they hit the robot. The problem with this is that the signals have
行进的距离比机器人和卫星之间的实际距离长。
travelled a longer distance than the actual distance between the robot and the satellite.
路径长度通过所谓的“多路径反射”而增加。所以
The path length has increased through what’s called ‘multi-pathed reflection’. So the
机器人内部的GPS接收器不知道这一点，所以它会出现错误
GPS receiver within the robot doesn’t know this, so it will come up with an erroneous
估计机器人的位置。这也是一个非常普遍的问题
estimate of where the robot is located. This is, again, quite a common problem with
GPS旁边是反映无线电波的大型结构。GPS估计机器人位置
GPS next to a big structure that reflects radio waves. The GPS estimated robot position
可能会出现严重错误。现在让我们考虑另一种情况。考虑
can be significantly in error. Now let’s consider another scenario. Consider
我们的机器人在地下，也许做一些采矿工作，这是一个非常重要的领域
that our robot is underground, perhaps doing some mining work, a really important domain
对于机器人。现在我们在这里遇到的问题是来自卫星的无线电波
for robots. Now the problem that we have here is that the radio waves from the satellite
无法穿透地球。
cannot penetrate the earth.
我们可能想要使用机器人的另一个应用是水下。我们又一次
Another application where we might want to use robots is underwater. And again we have
与我们在地下案件中遇到的问题相同。1.5千兆赫的无线电波不能
the same problem as we have in the underground case. The radio waves at 1.5 gigahertz cannot
深入水中。它们可能会穿透几毫米。所以这是一个机器人
penetrate very far into water. They perhaps penetrate a few millimetres. So a robot that’s
在任何深度都可以完全不使用GPS信息。
at any depth can make absolutely no use of GPS information.
现在让我们考虑一下我们在户外的情况，但机器人上方有树木。问题
Now let’s consider a situation we’re outdoors but there are trees above the robot. The problem
我们这里实际上与最后一个非常相似。叶子里有很多水
we have here is actually very similar to the last one. There is a lot of water in the leaves
树木，特别是在下雨之后，那里有很多水
of the trees, and particularly after it has been raining then there’s a lot of the water
在叶子的表面上。而这水从中吸收了1.5千兆赫的无线电波
on the surface of the leaves. And this water absorbs the 1.5 gigahertz radio waves from
卫星，它们不会穿透。所以用重型树冠GPS无线电波
the satellite, and they won’t penetrate. So with heavy tree canopy GPS radio waves
被吸收，我们不会获得足够的信息让机器人获得
are absorbed, and we’re not going to get enough information for the robot to obtain
修复。但是还有另一个也许是更深层次的原因
a fix. But there’s another and perhaps deeper reason
为什么GPS不是所有机器人问题的解决方案。考虑这种典型案例
why GPS is not the solution to all robotic problems. Consider this kind of typical case
我有一个机器人，它想要拿起一个物体。
where I’ve got a robot and it wants to pick up an object.
所以这个机器人想拿起那个香蕉。现在我可以为机器人添加GPS接收器，
So this robot wants to pick up that banana. Now I can add a GPS receiver to the robot,
所以机器人现在知道它在世界上的位置。但它并没有真正帮助，因为
so the robot now knows where it is in the world. But it doesn’t really help, because
它真的不知道香蕉在哪里。所以我可以在香蕉上添加GPS接收器，
it doesn’t really know where the banana is. So I can add a GPS receiver to the banana,
现在香蕉知道它在哪里;机器人知道它在哪里。但它仍然没有
and now the banana knows where it is; the robot knows where it is. But it still hasn’t
帮助这个机器人知道香蕉在哪里可以移动的问题
helped with this problem of this robot knowing where the banana is so that it can move and
抓住它。因此，为了获得有关香蕉位置的信息，我可以
grasp it. So in order to get information about the banana’s position to the robot I could
在香蕉上为这个GPS接收器添加一个无线电发射器，我可以添加一个接收器
add a radio transmitter to this GPS receiver on the banana, and I could add a receiver
到了机器人。所以现在机器人知道香蕉在哪里，它的坐标是
to the robot. So now the robot knows where the banana is, it has the coordinates of the
香蕉;它知道它在哪里，并且拥有这两条信息，机器人就可以了
banana; it knows where it is, and having those two pieces of information, the robot can then
计划一条路，以便从这里到达那里。现在虽然这可能有用，但基本
plan a path in order to get from here to there. Now while this might work, the fundamental
问题是机器人想要拾取，使用和操纵的每个对象
problem is that every object that the robot would want to pick up, work with and manipulate
需要配备这种仪器，显然这不是我们解决这个问题的方法
needs to be fitted with this kind of instrumentation, and clearly this is not the way we solve this
问题。如果我想拿起香蕉，我只需伸手去拿，我用眼睛锻炼身体
problem. If I want to pick up the banana I simply reach out, I use my eyes to work out
在哪里，并引导我的手，以便捡起它。
where it is and guide my hand in order to pick it up.